Yeah, we'll get you to sit back there until we move on to-
Yes, certainly.
Freightways, if you can hear me, we've got you up first, and we're expecting you to
turn on your camera.
Give them another 30 seconds to sort out their camera.
Hmm. Order starts there.
18.
Mm-hmm.
Leave two on.
Yeah.
Let's be out there at the defined time.
Okay, we might move to Customs first.
Are you happy
to present to the committee first, just because we don't have Freightways ready
to speak?
Yeah.
I think they need to accept the promotion.
Thank you.
We'll just get Customs up to the...
If you come up to the table.
Thanks very much. Thank you very much for making time to come to the committee.
We've written to you with a little bit of background on this complaint.
But in my experience, these hearings work really well if you give us a
short overview of what you've already provided to the committee, by
way of context, and then there will be questions from us to dig
into what we're still considering in terms of the levy making powers,
and
correct application of your legislative powers.
And that's where we stay. We're not interested in all of the facts, just
what's relevant to this committee. Over to you.
Oh, and please introduce yourself so we know.
Yeah, absolutely. So, I'm Richard Barge.
I'm the Deputy Chief Executive, Policy, Legal and Strategy at Customs.
I'm Olivia Norling, senior legal counsel for Customs.
And I'm John Waldrop. I'm a principal in the revenue policy team.
Okay. Thank you.
So,
thank you for inviting us to speak on this issue today.
We provided quite a fulsome response, I think, the best way
to describe it. And you did write back to us with a couple
of key points that you wanted to focus on.
So in terms of opening remarks, I'm going to
give some general points as well as focus on those two
questions, if that would be helpful.
So the changes that we made to goods cost recovery from one April this
year,
they were the culmination of a great deal of work, spanned several years, and
included extensive industry consultation and engagement.
We really had three main objectives for this piece of work.
We wanted to move to full cost recovery.
So we wanted the system to no longer have any taxpayer
subsidies, with some parts of the
fees and levies were charged to taxpayers.
We wanted to improve fairness for both fee payers and taxpayers, and we wanted to
make sure that the goods management system that we operate
on behalf of New Zealand was financially sustainable.
We think the work, and it's an extensive piece of work, we think we've achieved
those objectives.
And it was a culmination of a significant amount of
policy work,
and operational engagement and
consultation, including many meetings with industry.
So
you've specifically asked about the
equitability principle
and whether that was considered in calculating the levy rates.
So in
setting the levy rates and in going forward for consultation, we applied
the Order Office's good practice guide for setting and administering
fees and levies for cost recovery.
That guide sets out a core principle which talks about fairness and
equity as those who benefit from a service we provide,
or whose activities create the need for the service to be provided, should
meet the cost of providing it. So for Customs, we
clear and screen all imports and exports.
That comes at a cost. We provide a system to enable that
to happen. We receive information from importers and
exporters. The system operation comes at a cost.
We select goods out for intervention, examination,
ask for further information. There's cost associated with that.
There's a cost in risk goods in terms of investigations,
where we look to... There's a cost associated with the
process we may go through of inquiry and gathering evidence and trying to
identify who's responsible for the illicit shipment.
There's cost in our service delivery of the organization and
advice and support that we provide to
importers, exporters, businesses, consumers, et cetera.
So those are basically the activities that
we're looking to charge.
Fairness and equitability for levy payers means that they should
bear the costs of the services they create the needs for.
What that means is that they shouldn't shift their costs onto others.
Mm-hmm.
One of the points that we had in the previous system, there was a considerable
amount of cross subsidies where particular
streams of trade were paying for
other services.
Mm-hmm.
So for example, and this is totally relevant to this inquiry,
importers were covering the costs of customs going to search a ship when
we think the vessel owner should actually cover that cost of
service. They shouldn't also have other people's costs shifted onto them.
That's the same principle.
And there shouldn't be subsidies for taxpayers in particular
streams of trade that
gave them a competitive advantage over other streams of trade.
So one of our
significant concerns with this review was that mail
and fast freight,
a
significant amount of their costs were covered by taxpayers.
Whereas a retailer importing in high-value commercial
goods
had to pay full cost recovery. So we were very concerned about that when we started
that review.
When we undertook consultation, there was broad acknowledgement that the charges
should accurately reflect the costs that we incur for the service.
And I think it's a point that fairness does not mean that everyone pays the
same.
It means that they pay the costs for the activities they give rise to.
So that's how we applied that particular principle.
Do you mind if I just ask you a question about that too?
Absolutely.
A couple of times you've drawn sort of a distinction in the Auditor General's
guidelines between a proportional user pay system and
a causer pays system. And causer pays and
proportional user pays are different in those guidelines.
Are you describing, which one have you
applied here? Is it a causer pays, I think?
So the principle is if by importing or exporting a
consignment-
Yeah
... you cause us to have to do things.
Yes. Yeah.
And you should pay for the cost of us doing those things.
Okay, so we're not necessarily talking about equity and proportionality.
No.
We're talking about who causes you to have costs.
Yes.
Yeah.
We're talking about equity and that the costs land on the person
who caused the costs.
At the time.
Yeah.
Not spread. You don't spread the cost over time.
Not over time, but we do,
for administrative feasibility, have levies that relate to activities, and
they're spread over classes of levy payers.
Yeah.
So we don't have a particular fee calculated for every individual shipment.
It's for
each shipment of that class.
Okay.
Yeah.
Sorry, I did interrupt you.
No, that's all right.
Please continue, and then I know we have some questions from Joseph.
A very quick question. Thank you.
Thank you.
The letter you've received from minister sets out how the changes made the system
fairer. So just to point out that the move to consignment-based charging for goods
worth $1,000 or less eliminated a situation where some
freight firms were paying much less than others to clear a consignment.
So,
to explain,
we receive a cargo report from freight companies.
It could have anything from two consignments on it to
1,000.
We screen all 1,000 consignments,
and we screen the two consignments obviously.
Those importers who were clearing goods on 1,000 consignments were paying exactly
the same-
Yeah
... as someone who paid two. And we removed the tax-paid subsidies
for low-value goods carrying
as freight or mail.
It means that customs and MPI's costs to process imports
and exports are no longer unsubsidized or partially subsidized
or fully subsidized or have any cross subsidies depending on how they cross the
border.
I just want to point out that in setting the rates and the actual
charges for this review, we applied an activity-based costing
methodology that had been externally reviewed and deemed to be a
sound methodology for assessing the actual costs
of each activity we undertake, and
allocating those costs to a fee or levy rate.
So, in the example I will give,
low-value fast freight, there's a process for clearance of goods.
If an officer opens a package in that process, we
allocate the costs of that officer opening the package to that
activity. If the same officer the next day
goes and works in the airport and searches a bag,
then the cost of that activity is allocated to the border processing
levy for travelers,
and so on.
Okay.
So that's the process for that.
The complaint appears to argue that the levy differences for goods carried as fast
freight and mail are unfair and distort the market.
We just want to point out that the different
levies for fast freight and mail are different
because they are different services. They are different products.
They have different processes. They have different service standards, institutional
arrangements, and legal frameworks.
So the key difference is in detail.
Fast freight, for low-value commercial fast freight,
freight companies and carriers provide a cargo report to customs prior to
arrival, which we screen,
and MPI also screens. We select out items for intervention, and
we send electronic messages back to the freight company clearing the rest of
the consignment. So what that means is that service gives
those freight companies certainty, reliability, predictability, and
speed. And all of this generally, unless we get the report late, happens before
the goods land in New Zealand. We've been told for many, many
years by the freight companies that that is the service standard that they would
like to receive from us. And it gives them predictability that
the vast majority of items they import
can meet consumer and supplier expectations of delivery
times. Mail
is cleared by customs after arrival.
We don't receive the same amount of structured
data
We require, because we don't receive the same amount of structured data, we put
officers in the international mail center where they view packages,
letters, and cards. So we do not provide the same level of
service in terms of speed, reliability, and
predictability. So those are two quite distinct services.
Okay.
And that's why there's a differential between how we wanted
to charge mail and how we wanted to charge fast
freight. Following the Office of the Auditor guidelines that,
we should treat the two activities differently.
We are over time, but yeah, we'll have one question.
Thank you. You've helped sort of
clarify some of the questions I had, but it's still in the same vein.
Mm-hmm.
So the Universal Postal Union, which is the mail, but it's a
parcel that New Zealand Post is getting.
Is that right? And it's a parcel by parcels individual basis.
It's anything shipped under the Universal Postal Union.
But generally, it's a single parcel that New Zealand Post then needs to
or Customs needs to process for-
It includes letters, Christmas cards-
Yeah
... birthday cards as well.
So, there's a differential between that, as I'm understanding what you're
saying.
Yeah.
And fast freight, which is a bigger consignment, but in terms of
the causa
sort of principle, causa as you're having more
administrative costs. Is that what I'm understanding?
More administrative costs from the New Zealand Post for the
Universal Postal Union parcels as opposed to the
fast freight, which is a-
It's-
... a larger volume.
It's a manual process.
But simpler to process.
Yeah, it's a manual process, whereas the
fast freight process is easier for
us to process because we receive an electronic message.
Right.
But that requires investment in a system to
manage that process. So, for example,
when we mandated that process in 2019, there were about eight million
fast freight items a year. There's now 30 million, so that
system needs to manage all those transactions rapidly.
Oh, NZ Post doesn't have that system.
NZ Post does. Well, no. So NZ Post operates
in the fast freight service as a commercial operator as
well-
Okay
... under exactly the same terms and conditions as any other freight operator,
but UPU mail is a specific stream. Because of
restrictions on whether we can get data from overseas postal
authorities,
we don't provide the same degree of service.
If that made that clear.
Right. Okay.
Yeah. Sorry.
Abhi, thank you very much. We've run out of time.
Oh, that's okay.
But very much appreciate you.
Apologies, Chair. You did ask other specific questions in your letter,
so perhaps we can follow up on those points in writing?
Yeah. I think we might come back to you with further questions.
We don't
need any more information about consultation, but if you do want to just give us
any brief comments on the difference between
the weight-based
versus
per consignment aspect of the levy setting, then that is
something that is of interest to us.
Apologies. Can I just check one point?
There was also questions about the consultation process that we-
We don't have any more questions about that.
Okay. All right. That's great. Thank you.
Cool. Thank you.
Sure.
Freightways, you need to accept the promotion to panelist.
And that's done. Okay, great.
Hello, Mark.
Goodbye, Mark.
Hello. Hi.
Bloody hell, yeah, we've had all sorts of issues with technology.
No worries.
Apologies for that, but we're here now.
And I can probably make this bigger.
Just while you're sorting that. Oh, well done.
If you want to just quickly introduce yourselves.
You've got-
Yeah
... 10, 15 minutes with us.
And,
you now have the benefit of hearing what Customs has to say.
Our questions for you are similar.
So just spend a couple of minutes on what you've written to us, and then we'll ask
you some questions.
Perfect. Brilliant. Thanks very much for having us.
So I'm Mark Trowhere. I'm the CEO here at Freightways.
Been CEO here for around about eight years, and within the freight business for
about 30 years.
Hi, everybody. My name's Ruth Aiden, and I'm the general manager for
Freightways Global. So I look after, and have been looking after, the international
business for about the past two and a half years.
Thanks for having us. This has probably been quite a long, drawn-out,
frustrating process for us, trying to work with Customs to really
understand where it landed. So give you a real layman's view, but it's a
view that our customers would have and that we have of where the
charging regime has ended up. So the first point to make is we have no
objection paying our way. We pay our way with everything we
do, and we're more than happy. We don't want to see Customs or the
taxpayer put out and paying for services that are
incurred as a result of items we bring over the border.
So no issue with that.
What we do have an issue with, though, is that we believe the charging regime for
small items coming through either us or New Zealand Post as
mail are quite inequitable, and the service is actually
very similar.
And then the third impact, we think, is that we will have freight shifting
from a commercial stream where we provide really good data
to Customs on the item, where it's come from, who
it's going to. We give Customs the data to process
electronically, digitally, which should be really efficient.
We think more customers will shift to a mail stream because it's cheaper.
So those are the three points that we wanted to make.
The issue from our point of view is fairly simple.
So the regime that they've come out with for low-value goods-
Is it for any item coming through us will be charged $2.21
for customs and MPI.
But if it comes through New Zealand Post as a small packet, as a mail
packet, it'll be a $1.36 per kilogram.
Now, for a start, it's a different basis per kilo rather
than per item,
and the majority of these items are small, lightweight items.
So the
example I use a lot is a phone cover.
You buy a phone cover on Amazon, Temu, anywhere like that, you pay,
I don't know what a phone cover's worth, maybe it's 10 bucks.
You pay your $10 for a phone cover. That doesn't weigh a whole lot, it's about 200
grams. If that comes through Ruth's business
delivered by a Freightways company,
that'll cost $2.21.
If the exact same item from the exact same
sender to the exact same destination comes through the
mail stream,
it'll be charged at about 27 cents.
So 27 cents through mail, $2.21 through us,
and we would argue the services are actually very similar.
In fact,
if you line hauled that mail through to New Zealand,
on an aircraft, and most mail will arrive on an aircraft,
the delivery time for that item through mail will be very similar
to through courier. Maybe it's a day later, but it won't be much
difference on that.
And so what we think will happen is customs or customers will start to shift.
They'll see that that's cheaper. And it's an industry where it's really
finely balanced in terms of pricing, so customers shift for 10, 20
cents on the freight fee, let alone maybe a dollar,
$2
on that customs charge.
So, that's the big issue we have. Completely happy to pay our way, no problem
at all. The increase, for your information, in terms of what we're
paying will be about 1,200%. So from what we were
paying to what we will pay, 1,200% increase.
You don't get that every day. That doesn't come through in your rates, your
insurance, all the other things we think about with
inflation. I don't mind paying that as long as it's a level playing
field.
So just to reiterate on the commercial impact, this is
a very commoditized market, particularly in the Asian market.
It's very price sensitive because we're talking about really low-value goods.
So we can lose business for a mere 5 or 10 cents.
So when you're talking about a $2 difference, that's a huge
incentive for a customer to move channels, and that is
driven by a government levy, which by definition for us is market
distortion.
If we go back to the irony of all of this, I think as has been mentioned even by
customs themselves, the data is very important to them.
So getting sophisticated data helps them protect the border.
The earlier they get that data, the sooner they can evaluate the risk
of each of those parcels. We provide that data pretty much from the time
the freight is in the air, even before it lands.
So it doesn't seem right that we would be penalized
for doing the very thing that customs and MPI
is asking of the industry to do to protect the borders.
If we talk about the efficiency piece, everything we do from a
customs clearance and MPI clearance point of view is
electronic, and it's very fast. It's online.
So we're struggling to understand why that has a
higher cost to serve than the manual process that was
described in the NZ Post facility.
When that discussion was had with customs, when I challenged that, the
explanation that was given to me was not about the difference in
service, it was because NZ Post is effectively subsidizing
customs and MPI by giving them free rent, free car
parks, free systems. So of course, there's a lower cost to serve.
But it doesn't make sense or seem fair that because one
government organization is subsidizing another one, that that should set the
market rate. Levies by definition are supposed to empower them to set
an equal or reasonably equal levy across the
items. So,
making sure that the item
irrespective of which channel it goes through is charged the
same.
Thank you so much. I'm sure there are questions.
Can I just first ask,
if the system was all consignment based and not weight based,
do you think that would be... Is your submission that that was the more
equitable system?
Yes, I think it would be, but I think the charge would still have to be
the same. So we struggle to understand the
explanation we've had from customs is that New Zealand Post don't know how many
items they get, they only know the weight they get.
Now, I have seen the $200 million automatic
sortation systems they've put in place in New Zealand Post.
Mm.
And you can't tell me that they don't know how many items are coming through that
system. So that was the argument for kilos for them versus
items for us. So I think that is part of the story.
But the second part is the rate should be the same.
The piece that seems really strange is when you hear customs explain the
process at New Zealand Post, where there are people, there are dogs, there's
physical observation, they have no data, so they literally are looking at
items one by one.
Think about that process and the cost of that process, and then think about a
process where we only provide data and customs might ask to
see maybe two items out of a thousand.
Which of those sounds more efficient?
And I think it's ours.
Do... Okay.
I just thought I might make a comment because interesting point, and maybe you can
follow up this in writing with customs, that I did visit NZ Post new
sorting facility in South Auckland About two years ago, I think it was.
Yep.
It was highly sophisticated.
Yes, it is.
Very digitally enabled as well. So I am intrigued why there's a
differential being identified by customs between the two.
Yeah, I guess that's the same question as mine.
If everything was consignment based, but there was a rate that
reflected
the investment that customs has made versus a rate that
was for services that didn't
have that same level of investment, do you think that would be more fair?
I think it was really hard to get good information out of customs as
to why our rate was so high when compared to mail.
And they talked about transparency of costs,
but really, we didn't see much. And it seems to me maybe they're
charging us for some mystical IT system somewhere,
which costs a fortune, and that's why our rate is
so high, versus one is actually a very physical type
process at New Zealand Post, which is enabled by a whole lot of technology, a
whole lot of conveyors,
OCR readers, et cetera.
It just makes no sense to us. It's just really hard to understand why
we give data, they check it and come back and say, "Show us two items,"
versus they put the thousands of items over that New Zealand Post system
and have people observing and logs and do it manually,
and yet ours is the more expensive charge.
I think the other key point here is if we asked could we
have the same method of evaluating the freight as the
UPU network, in other words, we were happy to have MPI and Customs on
site if that were a cheaper way to obtain the service just
to create that level playing field, and that's just not an option that's available
to us. So that's just another example of an inequity there, even if we
wanted to strive to level the playing field by
doing it the same way, that's just not an option that's available.
Okay. Thank you. We have time for one more question, if there are any.
No,
really appreciate you coming along to the committee and for raising these
issues. The committee is going to consider
these issues
within the scope of our powers. We're not ComCom,
but we can look at that levy-making power and whether it complies with the
legislation. So we'll do that, and we'll write back to you.
Thank you.
Yeah. Thanks for having us.
Thanks for your time